C/C++ Pointers Cheatsheet

See examples in PointerExamples.cpp


Summary:

Pointer = * = variable containing address to a value.
Reference = & = Operator to get address from a variable, and also a type of variable which is like a const pointer. 


Pointer Declaration:

int * ptr (all three declarations mean the same thing)
int* ptr
int *ptr
int * ptr = &val (assign address of val using & reference)
int arr[10] (Array arr is actually a pointer to &arr[0] the address of the first element)
void func(string * strptr) (Passing in a pointer to a string)

Pointer Usage:

ptr - returns address of the value
*ptr - returns the value itself ("dereference")
**ptrptr - Pointer to pointer


Reference Declaration:

int & ref = val (Initialize with a value from a variable.  Cannot be a literal or not initialized)
int & ref = *ptr (Initialize from dereferenced ptr value)

Reference Usage:

ref - returns the value of the reference (automatic dereference).  Like *ptr.
&ref - returns the address of the reference.  Like ptr.

You can use & on any normal variable too.
Cannot change a reference once initialized.  Must be initialized, cannot be null, cannot point to pointers.

** For char * strings, cout treats the pointer specially.  It prints the whole string instead of just the first letter.


-------------------------------------------
https://tylerayoung.com/2014/04/30/c-pointers-references-cheat-sheet/
-------------------------------------------

The Golden Rule:
	If & is used to declare a variable, it makes that variable a reference.

	Otherwise, & is used to take the address of a variable.


Pointers:

	Initialization:
		int myInteger = 42;
		int * myIntPointer = &myInteger; // "address of"
		cout << *myIntPointer; // prints 42
	
	As a parameter:
		void foo( std::string * stringPtr ) {
		     cout << *stringPtr; // prints "Aloha"
		}
		std::string s = "Aloha";
		foo( &s ); // pass Aloha's address to the pointer


References:

	Pass-by-value:
		void foo( int x ) {
		     x = 42; // x is passed by value, so no change occurs outside this function
		}
		int x = 0;
		foo(x);
		// x == 0
	
	Pass-by-reference:
		void fooMutate( int &x ) {
		    x = 42; // passed by reference, so x changes outside this scope
		}
		
		int x = 0;
		fooMutate(x);
		// x == 42
	
	Declaring a reference (alias):
		int x = 0;
		int y = &x; // y is now an alias of x
		y = 42;
		// x == 42


-------------------------------------------
https://circuitsnsass.wordpress.com/2015/01/08/pointers-in-c-cheat-sheet/
-------------------------------------------

Pointers are tricky, and in C++ they’re especially tricky because of a piece of syntactic sugar known as a “reference” references are essentially pointers which de-reference themselves on impact. References can directly change the variable that is being pointed to without being de-referenced.

A reference uses the ampersand, however the ampersand is also used for the address in memory of a variable, as such you need to be careful with their use.

A short cheat sheet on references and pointers in C++

int x -creates integer variable
int *x -create a pointer to an integer
int &x -create a reference to a integer (note: references are different than pointers in C++)
*x -dereference pointer (get value out of the x variable in this case a int)
&x – gets the address of variable x (in this case the pointer address).
x -refers to the pointer ( doesn’t dereference, just points to address in memory)



-------------------------------------------
https://evanhahn.com/my-c-pointers-reference/
-------------------------------------------

In one of my C++ classes, we went over pointers and references. Because this stuff isn't second-nature to me, I made a little cheat-sheet, which is here if you'd like.

Declare a pointer
	int * foo;

Referencify
	int foo = 5;
	int * bar;
	bar = &foo;
	// *bar = 5
	foo = 6;
	// *bar = 6

Dereferencing
	int * foo;
	*foo = 5;
	*foo = 10;

Function pointers
	int (*foo)(int int) is a function that returns an integer and takes 2
	foo = min;
	foo = add;

Declaring arrays
	int array[5];

C strings
	char a[] = "foo";



-------------------------------------------
https://c-for-dummies.com/caio/pointer-cheatsheet.php
-------------------------------------------

Pointer Pointers:
-------------------
A pointer must always be of the same type as the variable it's pointing at.

Declaring a pointer variable does not create the type of variable it points at. It creates a pointer variable.

Though pointers are declared with an asterisk they are not always used with an asterisk.

The asterisk is the unary * operator. It is not the * multiplication operator.

Pointers must be initialized before they can be used.

Initialize a pointer by assigning it to a variable; the variable must be of the same type as the pointer.

To assign a pointer to a variable, use an ampersand with the variable's name.

The address-of unary operator & is not the same as the bitwise & AND operator.

	m_address = &memory;

To assign a pointer to an array, do not use the ampersand:

	s_address = string;

The pointer s_address would be used on the string array's elements.

To assign a pointer to an array element, use the ampersand:

	element = &string[2];

Without an asterisk, an initialized pointer holds a memory address.

With an asterisk, an initialized pointer references the value stored at its address.



Typical Pointer Setup and Use:
--------------------------------
First, create a pointer of the proper type:

	float *f;

Second assign it to a variable's memory location:

	f = &boat;

Finally, use the pointer:

	printf("%.0f",*f);


Without an asterisk, the pointer references a memory location.

With an asterisk, the pointer references the value at that memory location.

Always use the same type of pointer as the variables it examines: floats for floats, ints for ints, and so on.

Remember: initialize a pointer before you use it! Set the pointer equal to the address of some variable in memory.



Pointers, Parenthesis and Math:
--------------------------------
Pointer Thing	Memory Address				Memory Contents
-------------	--------------				---------------
p		Yep					Nope
*p		Nope					Yep
*p++		Incremented after value is read		Unchanged
*(p++)		Incremented after value is read		Unchanged
(*p)++		Unchanged				Incremented after it's used
*++p		Incremented before value is read	Unchanged
*(++p)		Incremented before value is read	Unchanged
++*p		Unchanged				Incremented before it's used
++(*p)		Unchanged				Incremented before it's used
p*++		Not a pointer				Not a pointer
p++*		Not a pointer				Not a pointer

The ++ operator is used above, though any math operation can be substituted.

A tip: Use parenthesis to isolate part of the pointer problem and the answer will always work out the way you intended.



Pointers and array brackets:
---------------------------------
Array Notation	Pointer Equivalent
--------------	------------------
array[0]	*a
array[1]	*(a+1)
array[2]	*(a+2)
array[3]	*(a+3)
array[x]	*(a+x)



Ugly ** notation:
------------------
Doodad		What It Is				Seen by The Compiler
------		----------				--------------------
array+1		An address				A pointer
*(array+1)	Contents of address, what lives there	A string
*(*(array+1))	Contents of a character array		A character
**(array+1)	Same as above				Same as above






-------------------------------------------
https://gist.github.com/peterflynn/7644af3d72b3aba20a96
-------------------------------------------

// If "const" is to the LEFT of "*" it applies to the object being pointed at
// If "const" is to the RIGHT of "*" it applies to the variable holding the pointer address

const T* ptr;  // object is immutable
T const* ptr;  //   "

T* const ptr;  // 'ptr' cannot be changed to point to a different address, but object is not immutable
               // (i.e. the variable is const, not the thing it points to)

const T* const ptr;  // object is immutable AND 'ptr' cannot be changed to point to a different address



-------------------------------------------
https://www.geeksforgeeks.org/pointers-vs-references-cpp/
-------------------------------------------

Pointers vs References:

Pointers: A pointer is a variable that holds memory address of another variable. A pointer needs to be dereferenced with * operator to access the memory location it points to.

References : A reference variable is an alias, that is, another name for an already existing variable. A reference, like a pointer is also implemented by storing the address of an object.
A reference can be thought of as a constant pointer (not to be confused with a pointer to a constant value!) with automatic indirection, i.e the compiler will apply the * operator for you.

	int i = 3; 

	// A pointer to variable i (or stores
	// address of i)
	int *ptr = &i; 

	// A reference (or alias) for i.
	int &ref = i; 

Differences:

Reassignment: 
A pointer can be re-assigned. This property is useful for implementation of data structures like linked list, tree, etc. See the following examples:

	int x = 5;
	int y = 6;
	int *p;
	p =  &x;
	p = &y;

On the other hand, a reference cannot be re-assigned, and must be assigned at initialization.

	int x = 5;
	int y = 6;
	int &r = x;

Memory Address: 
A pointer has its own memory address and size on the stack whereas a reference shares the same memory address (with the original variable) but also takes up some space on the stack. References may be passed to functions, stored in classes, etc. in a manner very similar to pointers.  Pointer is an independent variable and can be assigned NEW address values; whereas a reference, once assigned, can never refer to any new object until the variable goes out of scope.

NULL value: 
Pointer can be assigned NULL directly, whereas reference cannot. The constraints associated with references (no NULL, no reassignment) ensure that the underlying operations do not run into exception situation.

Indirection: 
You can have pointers to pointers to pointers offering extra levels of indirection. Whereas references only offer one level of indirection.

Arithmetic operations: 
Various arithmetic operations can be performed on pointers whereas there is no such thing called Reference Arithmetic.(but you can take the address of an object pointed by a reference and do pointer arithmetics on it as in &obj + 5).)


When to use What

The performances are exactly the same, as references are implemented internally as pointers. But still you can keep some points in your mind to decide when to use what :

Use references
In function parameters and return types.

Use pointers:
To implement data structures like linked list, tree, etc and their algorithms.
Use pointers if  pointer arithmetic or passing NULL-pointer is needed. For example for arrays (Note that array access is implemented using pointer arithmetic).



-------------------------------------------
http://www.cplusplus.com/doc/tutorial/pointers/
-------------------------------------------

(Long with lots of code and diagrams)


-------------------------------------------
http://www.ntu.edu.sg/home/ehchua/programming/cpp/cp4_pointerreference.html
-------------------------------------------

(Long with lots of code and diagrams)



-------------------------------------------
https://www.tutorialspoint.com/cprogramming/c_pointer_to_pointer.htm
-------------------------------------------

Pointer to Pointer

When we define a pointer to a pointer, the first pointer contains the address of the second pointer, which points to the location that contains the actual value.

A variable that is a pointer to a pointer must be declared as such. This is done by placing an additional asterisk in front of its name.

	int **var;

When a target value is indirectly pointed to by a pointer to a pointer, accessing that value requires that the asterisk operator be applied twice, as is shown below.

	#include <stdio.h>
	 
	int main () {				

	   int  var;
	   int  *ptr;
	   int  **pptr;

	   var = 3000;

	   /* take the address of var */
	   ptr = &var;

	   /* take the address of ptr using address of operator & */
	   pptr = &ptr;

	   /* take the value using pptr */
	   printf("Value of var = %d\n", var );
	   printf("Value available at *ptr = %d\n", *ptr );
	   printf("Value available at **pptr = %d\n", **pptr);

	   return 0;
	}

When the above code is compiled and executed, it produces the following result −

	Value of var = 3000
	Value available at *ptr = 3000
	Value available at **pptr = 3000



-------------------------------------------
https://www.geeksforgeeks.org/function-pointer-in-c/
-------------------------------------------

Function Pointers

In C, like normal data pointers (int *, char *, etc), we can have pointers to functions. 

Following is a simple example that shows declaration and function call using function pointer.

	#include <stdio.h> 
	// A normal function with an int parameter 
	// and void return type 
	void fun(int a) 
	{ 
	    printf("Value of a is %d\n", a); 
	} 
  
	int main() 
	{ 
	    // fun_ptr is a pointer to function fun()  
	    void (*fun_ptr)(int) = &fun; 
  
	    /* The above line is equivalent of following two 
	       void (*fun_ptr)(int); 
	       fun_ptr = &fun;  
	    */
  
	    // Invoking fun() using fun_ptr 
	    (*fun_ptr)(10); 
  
	    return 0; 
	} 




-------------------------------------------
https://www.tutorialspoint.com/cprogramming/c_pointer_to_an_array.htm
-------------------------------------------

Pointers and Arrays:

balance is a pointer to &balance[0], which is the address of the first element of the array balance. Thus, the following program fragment assigns p as the address of the first element of balance −

	double *p;
	double balance[10];

	p = balance;

It is legal to use array names as constant pointers, and vice versa. Therefore, *(balance + 4) is a legitimate way of accessing the data at balance[4].

Once you store the address of the first element in 'p', you can access the array elements using *p, *(p+1), *(p+2) and so on.




